{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The Sassanian king Khosrau II owned a napkin made of this material which he cleaned in a startling way in front of guests. Quebec's Thetford Hills were a major mining site for this material, which forms fibers approximately of the same size and shape of chromosomes. For 10 points, name this material once used for fireproofing, now known to cause mesothelioma.",
      "answer": "asbestos"
    },
    {
      "question": "The \"birdman cult\" emerged on this island, whose inhabitants have been divided into \"long- eared\" and \"short-eared\" groupings. This island, the key case study in Jared Diamond's book Collapse, has had its Polynesian natives ruled by Chile since 1888. For 10 points, name this Pacific island also called Rapa Nui, whose natives produced obsidian stone heads called moai.",
      "answer": "Easter Island"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event took place very close to a staged gladiatorial combat at the Theater of Pompey. During this event, Tillius Cimber grabbed the cloak of its target, who supposedly said the Greek phrase “kai su, teknon?” during it. This event targeted a man recently appointed “dictator in perpetuity”. For 10 points, name this action carried out on the ides of March by a group led by Brutus and Cassius.",
      "answer": "the assassination of Gaius Julius Caesar"
    },
    {
      "question": "These things made use of a part known as the Canadarm to manipulate outside objects. In the late 1970s, a partially-functional model of this kind of object, the Enterprise, was built. The Endeavour was the last created of these things; two of them, including the Columbia, were destroyed in accidents. For 10 points, name this kind of vessel that includes the Challenger.",
      "answer": "space shuttle"
    },
    {
      "question": "A failed action at this place was funded by the \"Secret Six\" and ended by then-U.S. army officer Robert E. Lee. This place was targeted because its placement at a junction of the B&O Railroad had made it an ideal storage site for army supplies, which were to be stolen for an insurrection. For 10 points, name this town, now in West Virginia, where John Brown launched a failed raid.",
      "answer": "Harpers Ferry"
    },
    {
      "question": "This author wrote about a plague in the year 2099 that kills everyone but Lionel Verney in The Last Man, which created the post-apocalyptic fiction genre. In another novel, this author created Robert Walton, who writes letters about the unjust execution of Justine Moritz. For 10 points, name this author who discussed a German scientist's creation of life in Frankenstein.",
      "answer": "Mary Shelley"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a painting by this artist exhibited at the 1863 Salon de Refuses, a nude Victorine Meurent stares at the viewer while she has a picnic with two fully clothed men. This artist based his depiction of a nude woman staring at the viewer on Titian’s Venus of Urbino. For 10 points, name this French Impressionist of Luncheon on the Grass and Olympia.",
      "answer": "Edouard Manet"
    },
    {
      "question": "Leaders of a 1967 coup in this country compared themselves to doctors temporarily placing democracy in a sling. The “regime of the colonels” fell after a Turkish invasion of Cyprus put down a coup this country supported. The United States supported anti-Communist forces here during its civil war in the late 1940s. For 10 points, name this country.",
      "answer": "Greece"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man received a gold medal as part of the men's eights team in the 1924 Olympic rowing competition. He later advocated universal health care as the People's Party's candidate in 1972. His published work was so ubiquitous that it was simply called \"the book.\" For 10 points, name this pediatrician who influenced the Baby Boomers with his book Baby and Child Care.",
      "answer": "Dr. Benjamin Spock"
    },
    {
      "question": "A classic simulator of this game included the Lovely Ladies, Ghastly Monsters, and American Dreams as teams. A 2009 simulator of this game contained a notorious error in which awards for the year \"216\" were presented. Early simulators of this game were named for Earl Weaver and Tony La Russa. For 10 points, name this sport played by Barry Bonds and Babe Ruth.",
      "answer": "baseball NHBB B 2014-2015"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Offshoots identified with this larger religion in the United States include the Five Percenters and Ten Percenters. Timothy Drew believed that a large number of Americans were descended from practitioners of this religion. Wallace Fard founded another American example of this religion. For 10 points, name this religion whose black practitioners in the U.S. included Malcolm X.",
        "answer": "Islam"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The black Muslim leader Louis Farrakhan organized what 1995 demonstration in Washington, D.C. which did not quite attract the number of people in its name?",
        "answer": "Million Man March"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man popularized the term \"NASCAR dads\" to explain the type of voter he wished to appeal to in addition to \"soccer moms.\" He designed the \"fifty-state strategy\" as head of the Democratic National Committee, which was a more successful effort than his own Presidential campaign. For 10 points, name this Vermont political who was embarrassed by a 2004 \"scream.\"",
        "answer": "Howard Dean"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What rival of Dean for the 2004 Democratic nomination was the former Supreme Commander of NATO who oversaw the 1999 Kosovo War?",
        "answer": "Wesley Clark"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This President chose to break the Great Railroad Strike. This man's election was secured when David Davis took a Senate seat, leaving Joseph Philo Bradley with the deciding vote on the Electoral Commission. This husband of the temperance advocate \"Lemonade Lucy\" won a contested election over Samuel Tilden. For 10 points, name this victor in 1876.",
        "answer": "Rutherford B. Hayes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Tilden had come to prominence and won the Democratic nomination after crusading against what Tammany Hall boss in New York?",
        "answer": "William \"Boss\" Tweed"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "James Nasmyth used six-way indexing to perfect precision milling, a key component of this idea. Eli Terry applied this concept to clock manufacture in 1814, and it was greatly refined in 1803 by Marc Brunel. For 10 points, identify this manufacturing concept pioneered in gunsmithing by Eli Whitney, in which components across a production run are identical.",
        "answer": "interchangeable parts"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Eli Whitney obtained an army contract to make muskets just as the \"Quasi-War,\" an undeclared naval war with what country, was beginning in 1798?",
        "answer": "France"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was repeated in Charleston upon the London and Magna Carta, and in Annapolis on the Peggy Stewart. This event was begun by the code words \"this meeting can do nothing more to save the country\" and inspired the passage of the first Intolerable Act. For 10 points, name this 1773 event in which the Sons of Liberty dressed as Mohawks and raided a British cargo ship.",
        "answer": "Boston Tea Party"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What leader of the Sons of Liberty and cousin of an American President was accused of organizing the Tea Party?",
        "answer": "Samuel Adams"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1997, this man succeeded Lionel Jospin (juice-PAN) as head of the Socialist Party, a post he held for a decade until his longtime partner Ségolène Royal (say-go-LEN roy-AL) lost a presidential election. In January 2014, he suffered a scandal over his relationship with Julie Gayet (guy-EH). For 10 points, name this current president of France.",
        "answer": "François Hollande"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hollande succeeded what leader of the UMP as president in 2012 after defeating his re- election bid?",
        "answer": "Nicolas Sarközy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man fought with the Rio Grande do Sul Republic while in exile in South America. This leader of the Red Shirts launched the Expedition of a Thousand, capturing the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies before ceding his captured territory to Victor Emmanuel II of Sardinia and his minister Count Cavour. For 10 points, name this key figure in Italian unification.",
        "answer": "Giuseppe Garibaldi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What unbending republican ally of Garibaldi founded the revolutionary society Young Italy and continued advocating democracy after reunification?",
        "answer": "Giuseppe Mazzini"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These people's kings performed a ritual in which they drew blood with a barbed cord, in order to worship their gods such as Chac. These people's mythology, which centered on the descent of the Hero Twins to the underworld Xibalba (shib-ALL-buh) to play the \"ball game,\" is collected in the Popul Vuh. For 10 points, name this Meso-American group that built Chichen Itza.",
        "answer": "Mayans"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Tikal site of Mayan ruins is found in what English-speaking country?",
        "answer": "Belize NHBB B 2014-2015"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "IMPEACHMENT OF ANDREW JOHNSON",
      "prompt": "During the impeachment of U.S. President Andrew Johnson, who or what…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Upper chamber of Congress conducted and voted on the removal trial?",
          "answer": "U.S. Senate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Party's \"Radical\" members pushed for the impeachment?",
          "answer": "Republican Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "Decade did the events take place during?",
          "answer": "1860s"
        },
        {
          "question": "Law was Johnson charged with violating?",
          "answer": "Tenure of Office Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "Person did Johnson fire to break that law?",
          "answer": "Edwin Stanton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Position did that person hold?",
          "answer": "Secretary of War"
        },
        {
          "question": "President Pro Tem of the Senate, who names a Reconstruction bill with Henry Davis, would have become President had the removal succeeded?",
          "answer": "Benjamin Wade"
        },
        {
          "question": "Became a subject of Profiles in Courage for casting the deciding vote against removal?",
          "answer": "Edmund Ross"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "FRENCH AND INDIAN WAR",
      "prompt": "During the French and Indian War, who or what was the…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern-day country which Britain acquired a large portion of as a result of the war?",
          "answer": "Canada"
        },
        {
          "question": "Young, then-British officer who surrendered Fort Necessity and later won at Trenton?",
          "answer": "George Washington"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name for the more general European conflict of which the war was a part?",
          "answer": "Seven Years War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battlefield outside Quebec where the war was decided?",
          "answer": "Plains of Abraham"
        },
        {
          "question": "British general who died commanding the decisive victory?",
          "answer": "James Wolfe"
        },
        {
          "question": "British-American painter who created a famous scene of that death?",
          "answer": "Benjamin West"
        },
        {
          "question": "French general who died commanding the decisive loss?",
          "answer": "Louis de Montcalm"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tribe which began the war allied with the British but switched sides in 1758 after a rebellion led by Big Mortar and Moytoy?",
          "answer": "Cherokee"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "ANCIENT GREEK WARRIORS",
      "prompt": "Which element of, foe of, or event involving, the ancient Greek military was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The battle from which news of Miltiades’s victory was relayed by Pheidippides, who ran about 26 miles?",
          "answer": "Battle of Marathon"
        },
        {
          "question": "The battle at which a force including Leonidas’s 300 Spartans attempted to hold off the invading Persians?",
          "answer": "Battle of Thermopylae"
        },
        {
          "question": "The rectangular formation of massed infantry favored by ancient Greek armies?",
          "answer": "phalanx formation"
        },
        {
          "question": "The name for spear-and-shield-wielding citizen-soldiers, taken from the term for their shields?",
          "answer": "hoplites"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Persian emperor, the third of his name, defeated by Alexander the Great at Gaugamela?",
          "answer": "Darius III"
        },
        {
          "question": "The battle at which Themistocles’s navy crushed Xerxes’s Persian fleet in the namesake strait?",
          "answer": "Battle of Salamis"
        },
        {
          "question": "The city-state at the head of the Boeotian League whose commander Epaminondas beat the Spartans at Leuctra?",
          "answer": "Thebes"
        },
        {
          "question": "The commander who introduced the sarissa and founded the League of Corinth after winning the Battle of Chaeronea?",
          "answer": "Philip II of Macedon NHBB B 2014-2015"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was encouraged to develop his alcoholism by the harsh General Sutgof (SOOT- goff), who commanded the Cadet School where he won an appointment to the Preobrazhensky (pree-AH-bruh-ZEN-skee) Regiment of the Imperial Guard. He was criticized by his mentor (20 pts)",
        "Mily Balakirev (buh-LAH-kee-rev) for his tone poem about a (10 pts)",
        "witches' sabbath, Night on Bald Mountain. For 10 points, name this Russian composer of Pictures at an Exhibition."
      ],
      "answer": "Modest Mussorgsky"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Kurt Shmoke's 2013 article on this President's little-known civil rights record discussed his advocacy of increasing funding for the medical college at Howard University. This man, who repeatedly vetoed the McNary-Haugen farm relief bill, agreed to the (20 pts)",
        "Kellogg- Briand Pact outlawing war. He came to prominence as the governor of (10 pts)",
        "Massachussetts, where he broke the Boston police strike. For 10 points, name this taciturn successor of Warren Harding."
      ],
      "answer": "Calvin Coolidge"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group was tricked into releasing 15 hostages in Operation Jaque, and its leader currently has the alias Timochenko. Three IRA members, James Monaghan, Martin McCauley, and Niall Connolly, were accused of teaching this group (20 pts)",
        "bomb-making. This group was originally founded after an attack on the Marquetalia Republic, which was founded after La (10 pts)",
        "Violencia. For 10 points, name this terrorist group and cocaine smuggling outfit based in Colombia."
      ],
      "answer": "FARC"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Note to moderator: This question has a complex answer line. Please examine it for a moment before beginning to read. The territorial waters of these two countries are separated by the Northern Limit Line. The Bridge of No Return allowed passage between these two countries until 1976, when the bridge was closed following Operation (20 pts)",
        "Paul Bunyan, a response to the Axe Murder Incident. These two countries were required by a 1953 (10 pts)",
        "armistice to establish a four-kilometer buffer now known as the Demilitarized Zone. For 10 points, name these rival countries on an East Asian peninsula."
      ],
      "answer": "North Korea and South Korea"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This empire's legendary founder used an arrow tipped with a rooster claw to defeat the Soso confederacy. The Sankore school was built by this empire, whose people were ethnically (20 pts)",
        "Mandinka. A powerful ruler of this empire loaded 300 camels with (10 pts)",
        "gold to donate while on hajj. For 10 points, name this West African empire founded by Sundiata and led by Mansa Musa, which was the regional power between Ghana and Songhai and profited from trade in Timbuktu."
      ],
      "answer": "Mali Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This king launched an invasion of the Netherlands to claim the inheritance of his wife Maria Theresa of Spain. As a child, his chambers were invaded by an angry mob during the civil war known as the Fronde. As king, this man revoked the Edict of (20 pts)",
        "Nantes and sparked the War of the Spanish Succession by proclaiming his grandson (10 pts)",
        "Philip V king of Spain. For 10 points, name this King of France who created the palace of Versailles and who was known as “The Sun King.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Louis XIV"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country’s leaders received a dead dog from Henry the Fowler before the Battle of Riade. This country’s Black Army was founded by the son of John Hunyadi, Matthias Corvinus. Otto the Great stopped this country’s westward expansion at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Lechfield. A member of the Arpad dynasty, (10 pts)",
        "Stephen I, converted this country to Christianity, and it was formed by the Magyar tribe. For 10 points, name this country with capital at Budapest."
      ],
      "answer": "Hungary"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In his first Olympics, this man faced controversy over claims he threw his qualification race to allow Shani Davis to make the Olympic team. In that same Olympics he was awarded gold after the South Korean winner was disqualified for illegally (20 pts)",
        "blocking him. In 2007, this athlete competed in and won the spring season of (10 pts)",
        "Dancing with the Stars. For 10 points, name this Olympic speed skater, who, with four bronzes, two silvers, and two gold medals, is the most decorated American Winter Olympic athlete of all time."
      ],
      "answer": "Apolo Anton Ohno NHBB B 2014-2015"
    }
  ]
}